<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor of the famous city of London, the Honourable the sheriffs, aldermen, Common Council, and all worthy citizens of the same, the humble address of Anthony Wildgoos, workman-printer in divine meditations on death, made upon these nine words, nothing more sure then death, for all must die.</title>
            <author>Wildgoos, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18394379</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18394379</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1136:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Right Honourable, the Lord Mayor of the famous city of London, the Honourable the sheriffs, aldermen, Common Council, and all worthy citizens of the same, the humble address of Anthony Wildgoos, workman-printer in divine meditations on death, made upon these nine words, nothing more sure then death, for all must die.</title>
                  <author>Wildgoos, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Anthony Wildgoos ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[164-?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Within mourning borders.</note>
                  <note>Includes woodcut illustration.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Meditations.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:107473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Right Honourable, The Lord Mayor of the famous City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Sheriffs, Aldermen, Common Council, and all Worthy Citizens of the ſame, the Humble Addreſs of <hi>Anthony Wildgoos</hi> Workman-Printer: IN DIVINE MEDITATIONS ON DEATH, Made upon theſe Nine WORDS, Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Die.</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing</hi> MOre wiſh'd than Wealth, yet that muſt leave us;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing</hi> More ſweet than Love, that laſts not ever:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>NothingMore</hi> dear than Friends, yet they'll deceive us;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing</hi> More faſt than Wedlock, yet they ſever.</l>
               <l>The World muſt end, all things away muſt fly:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Dye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>More</hi> Strength may be obtain'd, but 'twill decay;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More</hi> Beauty may be had, but 'twill not laſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More</hi> Honour may be got, but 'twill away;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>More</hi> Joys may follow, but theſe ſoon are paſt.</l>
               <l>For long continuance, it's in vain to try.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You, and you, and you, and all muſt Dye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sure</hi> Love muſt Die, though rooted in the Heart;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sure</hi> 'Tis, that all things earthly are unſtable:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sure</hi> Friends are pure friends, yet ſuch friends muſt part;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sure</hi> 'Tis, that all things (here) are variable.</l>
               <l>Not two nor one may ſcape; nor thou, nor I;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Let the Rich no longer covet Wealth;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Let the Proud vail his ambitious Thought;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Let the Sound not glory in his Health:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then</hi> Let all yield, ſince all muſt come to nought.</l>
               <l>For long Continuance, it's vain to try:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Dye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death</hi> Took away King <hi>Herod</hi> in his Pride,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death</hi> Spar'd not <hi>Hercules</hi> for all his ſtrength;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death</hi> Struck Great <hi>Alexander</hi> that he dy'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death</hi> Long ſpar'd <hi>Adam,</hi> yet he dy'd at length.</l>
               <l>The Beggar and the King, the Low, the High;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Dye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> Scepters, Crowns, Imperial Diadems;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> All the Beauties that on Earth do live:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> Pleaſures, Treaſures, Jewels, coſtly Jems;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For</hi> All the Glory that the World can give,</l>
               <l>Death will not ſpare his Dart, but ſtill reply,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You, and you, and you, and all muſt Dye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>All</hi> From the higheſt, to the loweſt Degree;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All</hi> Nations, People, Kingdoms, Countries, Lands,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All</hi> In the Earth, or Air, or Sea, that be,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All</hi> Muſt yield up to his all-conquering Hands:</l>
               <l>He wounds them all with an Impartial Eye:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſt</hi> All then Die; then all muſt think on Death:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſt</hi> All things vaniſh? Sun, and Moon, and Stars?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſt</hi> Every ſingle Creature yield his Breath?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſt</hi> All things ceaſe, our Joys, Delights, our Cares?</l>
               <l>Yes, All with an united voice do cry,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Die</hi> Let us then, but let us Die in peace;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Die</hi> To our Sins, that dying we may live:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Die</hi> To the World, that Grace may more increaſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Die</hi> Here, to live with him that life doth give,</l>
               <l>Die, die we muſt; let Wealth and Pleaſures lie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing more ſure then Death, for all muſt Die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man the firſt Garden-Flower in</hi> Eden <hi>faded;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man the firſt Building, the firſt</hi> Babel <hi>prov'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man the firſt rais'd, was Man the firſt degraded;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man was firſt ſhook, that might have liv'd unmov'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death's breath o'r Flowers and Towers hath like Commanding;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Hand pull'd down, Man rais'd, ſhook Man firm-ſtanding.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Anthony Wildgoos,</hi> dwelling within <hi>Cripple-Gate,</hi> near <hi>Lamb</hi>'s Chappel Gate.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
